<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="25"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[renaissance_sas

                            Sri Aurobindo on Sri Krishna
        journal.aurobharati.in






















































































                                                                                                                                                                         An offering from Renaissance journal]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[renaissance_sas
                                                                                                                                                                                                                              journal.aurobharati.in]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Sri Aurobindo on the Historicity of








                                                                                                       Sri Krishna
















                   The historicity of Krishna is of less spiritual







                   importance and is not essential, but it has still a








                   considerable value. It does not seem to me that







                   there can be any reasonable doubt that Krishna the








                   man was not a legend or a poetic invention but








                   actually existed upon earth and played a part in the







                   Indian past.









                                                                                                                         contd...]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Two facts emerge clearly, that he was regarded as an important





                      spiritual figure, one whose spiritual illumination was recorded in one






                      of the Upanishads, and that he was traditionally regarded as a divine






                      man, one worshipped after his death as a deity; this is apart from the





                      story in the Mahabharata and the Puranas. There is no reason to





                      suppose that the connection of his name with the development of the






                      Bhagavata religion, an important current in the stream of Indian






                      spirituality, was founded on a mere legend or poetic invention.













                                                                                                                                                                                         (CWSA, 28: 482-483)








                renaissance_sas

           journal.aurobharati.in]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[More on the Historicity of Sri Krishna











                         The Mahabharata is a poem and not history, but it is clearly






                         a  poem  founded  on  a  great  historical  event,  traditionally






                         preserved in memory; some of the figures connected with






                         it, Dhritarashtra, Parikshit, for instance, certainly existed






                         and  the  story  of  the  part  played  by  Krishna  as  leader,







                         warrior and statesman can be accepted as probable in itself






                         and to all appearance founded on a tradition which can be






                         given a historical value and has not the air of a myth or a






                         sheer poetical invention.






                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     contd. . .]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[continued from previous page






                                                                                                                                 That is as much as can be






                                                                                                                                 positively said from the point of







                                                                                                                                 view of the theoretical reason as






                                                                                                                                 to the historical figure of the






                                                                                                                                 man Krishna; but in my view







                                                                                                                                 there is much more than that in






                                                                                                                                 it and I have always regarded the






                                                                                                                                 incarnation as a fact and







                                                                                                                                 accepted the historicity of






                                                                                                                                 Krishna as I accept the







                                                                                                                                 historicity of Christ.






                                                                                                                                                                                                                (CWSA, 28: 483)]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[When Sri Aurobindo wrote to a disciple who had Sri Krishna







                                                                                                           as his iṣṭa-deva










               ... your turn towards Krishna was not an obstacle....I affirm that





               positively in answer to your question. If we consider the large and indeed





               predominant part he played in my own sadhana, it would be strange if





               the part he has in your sadhana could be considered objectionable.








               Sectarianism is a matter of dogma, ritual etc., not of spiritual





               experience; the concentration on Krishna is a self-offering to the iṣṭa-






               deva. If you reach Krishna you reach the Divine; if you can give yourself





               to him, you give yourself to me. Your inability to identify may be because





               you are laying too much stress on the physical aspects, consciously or





               unconsciously.





                                                                                                                                                                                                                          (CWSA, 35: 431)]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[“What Krishna must I challenge...”
















               "You can’t expect me to argue about my own spiritual








               greatness in comparison with Krishna‘s. The question








               itself would be relevant only if there were two sectarian








               religions in opposition, Aurobindoism and








               Vaishnavism, each insisting on its own God’s









               greatness. That is not the case.











                                                                                                                                                                                        contd....]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[continued from previous page









                   And then what Krishna must I challenge,—the Krishna of the







                   Gita who is the transcendent Godhead, Paramatma,







                   Parabrahma, Purushottama, the cosmic Deity, master of the







                   universe, Vasudeva who is all, the immanent in the heart of all







                   creatures, or the Godhead who was incarnate at Brindavan and







                   Dwarka and Kurukshetra and who was the guide of my Yoga







                   and with whom I realised identity?]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[continued from previous page
                                                                                                                                                                              All that is not to me
                                                                                                                                                                              All that is not to me





                                                                                                                                                                              something
                                                                                                                                                                              something






                                                                                                                                                                              philosophical or mental
                                                                                                                                                                              philosophical or mental






                                                                                                                                                                              but a matter of daily and
                                                                                                                                                                              but a matter of daily and






                                                                                                                                                                              hourly realisation and
                                                                                                                                                                              hourly realisation and





                                                                                                                                                                              intimate to the stuff of
                                                                                                                                                                              intimate to the stuff of






                                                                                                                                                                              my consciousness. Then
                                                                                                                                                                              my consciousness. Then






                                                                                                                                                                              from what position can
                                                                                                                                                                              from what position can






                                                                                                                                                                              I adjudicate this
                                                                                                                                                                              I adjudicate this






                                                                                                                                                                              dispute?
                                                                                                                                                                              dispute?









                                                                                                                                                                                                         (Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 35: 431-432)
                                                                                                                                                                                                         (Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 35: 431-432)]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[SRI KRISHNA IN BRINDAVAN














                   The story of Brindavan is another matter; it does not enter







                   into the main story of the Mahabharata and has a Puranic







                   origin and it could be maintained that it was intended all







                   along to have a symbolic character. At one time I accepted







                   that explanation, but I had to abandon it afterwards; there is







                   nothing in the Puranas that betrays any such intention.



















                                                                                                                                                                                                                                contd...]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[SRI KRISHNA IN BRINDAVAN
                                                                       SRI KRISHNA IN BRINDAVAN






                                                                                                       (contd. from previous page)
                                                                                                       (contd. from previous page)










                         It seems to me that it is related as something that actually
                          It seems to me that it is related as something that actually





                         occurred or occurs somewhere; the Gopis are to them realities
                          occurred or occurs somewhere; the Gopis are to them realities





                         and not symbols. It was for them at the least an occult truth,
                          and not symbols. It was for them at the least an occult truth,





                         and occult and symbolic are not the same thing; the symbol
                          and occult and symbolic are not the same thing; the symbol





                         may be only a significant mental construction or only a
                          may be only a significant mental construction or only a





                         fanciful invention, but the occult is a reality which is actual
                          fanciful invention, but the occult is a reality which is actual





                         somewhere, behind the material scene as it were and can have
                          somewhere, behind the material scene as it were and can have





                         its truth for the terrestrial life and its influence upon it, may
                          its truth for the terrestrial life and its influence upon it, may





                         even embody itself there.
                          even embody itself there.





                                                                                                                                                                                                               (CWSA, 28: 483)]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[THE LILA OF THE GOPIS














                       The lila of the Gopis seems to be conceived as something which







                      is always going on in a divine Gokul and which projected itself






                      in an earthly Brindavan and can always be realised and its







                      meaning made actual in the soul. It is to be presumed that the






                      writers of the Puranas took it as having been actually projected






                      on earth in the life of the incarnate Krishna and it has always







                      been so accepted by the religious mind of India.






                                                                                                                                                                                                  (CWSA, 28: 483-484)]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[MORE ON THE LILA OF THE GOPIS















                         The Gopis are not ordinary people in the proper sense of the word






                         —they are extraordinary by their extremeness of love, passionate






                         devotion, unreserved self-giving. Whoever has that, however






                         humble his position in other respects, learning, external sanctity






                         etc. etc., can easily follow after Krishna and reach him; that seems






                         to me the sense of the symbol of the Gopis. There are many other






                         significances, of course—that is only one among the many.






















                                                                                                                                                                                                                        (CWSA, 29: 493)]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[What Matters is the Contact with Krishna













                       These questions and the speculations to which they have







                      given rise have no indispensable connection with the







                      spiritual life. There what matters is the contact with







                      Krishna and the growth towards the Krishna







                      consciousness, the presence, the spiritual relation, the







                      union in the soul and, till that is reached, the aspiration,







                      the growth in bhakti and whatever illumination one can







                      get on the way.













                                                                                                                                                                                                                           (contd.....)]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[continued from previous page




            To one who has had these







            things, lived in the presence,







            heard the voice, known Krishna







            as Friend or Lover, Guide,






            Teacher, Master or, still more,







            has had his whole consciousness







            changed by the contact, or felt






            the presence within him, all such







            questions have only an outer and







            superficial interest.






                                                                                                                               (contd.....)]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[continued from previous page








                                                                                                                                     So also, to one who has had








                                                                                                                                     contact with the inner







                                                                                                                                     Brindavan and the lila of the







                                                                                                                                     Gopis, made the surrender








                                                                                                                                     and undergone the spell of







                                                                                                                                     the joy and the beauty or even







                                                                                                                                     only turned to the sound of







                                                                                                                                     the flute, the rest hardly








                                                                                                                                     matters.







                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             (contd...)]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[continued from previous page






             But from another point of view, if one





             can accept the historical reality of the






             incarnation, there is this great spiritual






             gain that one has a point d’appui for a






             more concrete realisation in the






             conviction that once at least the Divine





             has visibly touched the earth, made the






             complete manifestation possible, made






             it possible for the divine supernature to






             descend into this evolving but still very





             imperfect terrestrial nature.






                                                                                                                      (CWSA, 28: 484)]]></page></pages></Search>