<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="12"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[EGOISM, VANITY AND PRIDE:





                                                     Becoming Conscious with Guidance from





                                                                                                           Sri Aurobindo










                                                 Researched and curated by Renaissance team]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Human nature is shot through in all its stuff with the






                             threads of the ego. Even when one tries to get away






                             from it, it is in front or walks behind all the thoughts







                             and actions like one’s shadow.









                             To see that is the first step—to discern the falsity and






                             absurdity of the ego movements is the second—to







                             discourage and refuse it at every step is the third—but






                             it goes entirely only when one sees, experiences and






                             lives the One in everything and equally everywhere.












                             ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 217-218]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[The human consciousness is






                                                                                                              permeated in all its past ideas with





                                                                                                              this substance of egoism. It is only by






                                                                                                              a constant quiet vigilance and






                                                                                                              increasing consciousness that it can






                                                                                                              be got out—for if it is not allowed to






                                                                                                              play openly, it conceals itself and






                                                                                                              takes subtle and disguised forms.













                                                                                                              ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 218]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[...pride of the ego is the case with all human






                   beings. All the action is shot through with ego,






                   acts, feelings, thoughts, everything, big or small,






                   good or bad. Even humility and what is called






                   altruism is with most people only a form of ego.






                   It does not depend on having something to be






                   proud of.










                   ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 217]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[PRIDE IS ONLY ONE FORM OF EGO—THERE ARE TEN






                   THOUSAND OTHERS. EVERY ACTION OF MAN IS FULL OF






                   EGO—THE GOOD ONES AS WELL AS THE BAD, HIS






                   HUMILITY AS MUCH AS HIS PRIDE, HIS VIRTUES AS





                   MUCH AS HIS VICES.







                   To get the ego out of the human nature is not so simple as





                   that. If one is free from ego, does nothing with reference to





                   himself or for his own sake but only for the Divine and all his





                   thoughts and feelings are for the Divine, then he is





                   Jivanmukta and a Siddha Yogi.





                                                                                                                                                                                     ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 241]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[EGO IS A VERY CURIOUS THING AND IN NOTHING MORE






                       THAN IN ITS WAY OF HIDING ITSELF AND PRETENDING






                                                                                               IT IS NOT THE EGO.










                                              It can always hide even behind an aspiration to






                                                                                                    serve the Mother.










                                            The only way of getting rid of it is to chase it out






                                                                                     of all its veils and corners.












                                                                                          ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 232]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[HUMAN NATURE HAS ALWAYS BEEN





                                       EGOISTIC IN ITS BASIS AND SO IT BRINGS IN






                                       THE EGO MOTIVE INTO THE WORK FOR THE





                                       DIVINE ALSO.












                                       That can only be overcome slowly, for what is ingrained




                                       in the human vital nature and has been active through




                                       hundreds of lives cannot disappear at once.







                                       To be conscious and to have the steady will to change and




                                       make the inner motive of bhakti and self-giving prevail




                                       over the outer motives is the one thing necessary.










                                                                                              ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 219]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Ambition and vanity are things so natural to






                                            the human consciousness—they have even







                                            their use in ordinary life—that it is quite






                                            natural that at first they should enter into






                                            the sadhana also and linger even when they






                                            are rejected.









                                            But they have to be pushed out, before one is






                                            far on the path—otherwise they are very






                                            dangerous attendants and can pervert both






                                            aspiration and siddhi.











                                                                                                                                                                             ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 239]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[People who live in the vital and have much vanity . . .








                            easily get the idea that they have attained everything, are







                          without ego, all they receive is from the Divine (even when







                           a magnified ego is driving them) etc. etc., for the vital ego







                           is eager to arrive, to be big, to be siddha, and it persuades







                                                          itself very easily that it is all these things.













                                                                                           ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 240]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[... just as the rajasic ahankara which exalts itself







                                                  unduly is not good for the sadhana, creating







                                                    pride, vanity and delusion, so this opposite







                                                     thing, called often tamasic ahankara, is not






                                          good, for it creates diffidence, despondency and







                                                                                             in some people inertia.















                                                                                           ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 225]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[THE TAMASIC EGO is that which accepts and supports






                          despondency, weakness, inertia, self-depreciation,






                          unwillingness to act, unwillingness to know or be open,






                          fatigue, indolence, do-nothingness.








                          Contrary to the rajasic it says, “I am so weak, so obscure, so miserable,





                          so oppressed and ill-used—there is no hope for me, no success, I am





                          denied everything, I am unsupported—how can I do this, how can I do





                          that, I have no power for it, no capacity, I am helpless; let me die; let





                          me lie still and moan,” etc. etc. Of course not all that at once or in




                          every case; but I am giving the general character of the thing.







                                                                                                                                                                          ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 31: 225-226]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[For more such inspiring quick reads,
                                                                        For more such inspiring quick reads,




                                                                 visit the website of Renaissance Journal:
                                                                 visit the website of Renaissance Journal:








                                                              HTTPS://JOURNAL.AUROBHARATI.IN/
                                                               HTTPS://JOURNAL.AUROBHARATI.IN/]]></page></pages></Search>