<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="14"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[A Renaissance Journal offering


                                                                                                 http://renaissance.aurosociety.org














                                                                               ु
                                   सव स त  नरामयाः
















                         May All be Free from Illness]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[All Nature dumbly calls to her alone



       To heal with her feet the aching throb of life




       And break the seals on the dim soul of man




       And kindle her fire in the closed heart of things.








                                                                             ~ Sri Aurobindo, Savitri, p. 314






                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[In  the  ancient  conception  of  the  universe




        our  material  existence  is  formed  from  the




        five elemental states of Matter, the ethereal,




        aerial, fiery, liquid and solid; everything that




        has  to  do  with  our  material  existence  is




        called the elemental, adhibhūta.





                                                                                           ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 18: 18




                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Good health is the exterior





                       expression of an inner harmony.








                                                                         ~ The Mother, CWM 15: 136
















                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Physical ailments are always the sign of




         a resistance in the physical being; but




         with surrender to the Divine’s Will and





         a complete trust in the working of the




         Grace, they are bound to disappear soon.








                                                                        ~ The Mother, CWM 15: 137




                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[If  you  want  to  get  cured  there  are  two





             conditions.  First  you  must  be  without




             fear, absolutely fearless, you understand,





             and  secondly  you  must  have  a  complete




             faith in the Divine protection. These two




             things are essential.                                                          ~ The Mother, CWM 15: 141









                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[If you are ill, your illness is looked after




          with  so  much  anxiety  and  fear,  you  are




          given  so  much  care  that  you  forget  to




          take  help  from  the  One  who  can  help




          you and you fall into a vicious circle and




          take a morbid interest in your illness.








                                                                                      ~ The Mother, CWM 15: 144




                                                                                                renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Do not love your ill health and






                    the ill health will leave you.









                                                                               ~ The Mother, CWM 15: 146
















                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[The healthiest ages of mankind






          were those in which there were







               the fewest material remedies.










                                                                                ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 12: 475










                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[We  ought  to  use  the  divine  health  in  us





         to  cure  and  prevent  diseases;  but  Galen




         and Hippocrates & their tribe have given





         us  instead  an  armoury  of  drugs  and  a




         barbarous Latin hocus-pocus as our





         physical gospel.






                                                                      ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 12: 476




                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[The spirit within us is the only all-





             efficient  doctor  and  submission  of





             the body to it the one true panacea.








                                                                     ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 12: 476













                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[It  should  take  long  for  self-cure  to



              replace  medicine,  because  of  the  fear,




              self-distrust  and  unnatural  physical




              reliance  on  drugs  which  Medical




              Science  has  taught  to  our  minds  &




              bodies & made our second nature.






                                                                        ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 12: 477




                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[It  is  not  the  medicine  that  cures  so




           much  as  the  patient’s  faith  in  the




           doctor  and  the  medicine.  Both  are  a





           clumsy  substitute  for  the  natural  faith




           in  one’s  own  self-power  which  they




           have themselves destroyed.







                                                                            ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 12: 475






                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Medicine  is  necessary  for  our  bodies  in




          disease  only  because  our  bodies  have




          learned the art of not getting well without




          medicines.  Even  so,  one  sees  often  that





          the  moment  Nature  chooses  for  recovery




          is  that  in  which  the  life  is  abandoned  as




          hopeless by the doctors.




                                                                        ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 12: 477




                                                                                                 renaissance.aurosociety.org]]></page></pages></Search>