<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="9"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[PHYSICAL EDUCATION IN ANCIENT INDIA





















                                                   SOME EXCERPTS








                                                                        From







                               BHĀRATA SHAKTI EXHIBITION







                                                           Organised by








                                        RENAISSANCE JOURNAL



                                      SRI AUROBINDO SOCIETY





















                                                 Sri Aurobindo Ashram



                                       Exhibition House, Pondicherry


                                                                MAY 2022



                                                                                                        Research & Curation: Beloo Mehra
                                                                                                  Design Assistance: Biswajita Mohapatra]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[EDUCATION OF THE BODY







           India has had a long history of physical education. The heroes that


           India gave to herself represent not only great qualities of courage

           and valour but also of physical strength and excellence. Examples

           include Valmiki’s description of Rama and Vyasa’s descriptions of


           Arjuna and Bhima.




                                                                           ***























           We find many prayers in our scriptures where the aspirant seeks

           strength:





                                            बलं धहि तनूषु नो बलमिन्द्रानळुत्सु नः।
                                                      े

                                      बलं तोकाय तनयाय जीवसे त्वं हि बलदा अमस॥

            Equip our body with strength, O lndra, shower strength in our bulls.

           Shower strength for life on our progeny. You are verily the bestower

                                                                  of strength.


                                                            (Rigveda, 3.53.18)








                                                                                                  े
                                                बलन लोकस्ततष्ठतत बलिुपाततवतत ॥
                                                     े
         The existence of the world is dependent on strength. Be devoted to strength.

                                                 (Chandogya Upanishad 7.8. l )]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Aspiration for Strength











                                                                      े
                              तेजोऽमस तेजो ितय धहि। वीययिमस वीयय ितय धहि॥
                                                                                                                    े
                                                                  े
                             बलिमस बलं ितय धहि। ओजोऽमस ओजो ितय धहि॥
                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                                     े
                                                                      े
                             िन्द्युरमस िन्द्यु         ं ितय धहि । सिोऽमस सिो ितय धहि॥

                            Thou art splendour; bestow splendour on me.


                                 Thou art potency, bestow potency on me.

                                Thou art strength, bestow strength on me.


                                      Thou art virility, bestow virility on me.

                        Thou art force of action, bestow the same on me.


                               Thou art prowess, bestow prowess on me.


                                                          (Yajurveda, 19.9)













































           The ancient Sanskrit adage "Shariram aadyam khalu dharma-saadhanam"

            (a sound body is the veritable instrument of the pursuit of the ideal law of

                              life) underlined the importance of physical education.]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[During the Vedic and the Upanishadic periods, and even later, there


             was an emphasis on the pursuit of an integral aim of life, which
             determined the discipline of integral education. Both the material and


             spiritual poles of the being had their place in this system.




             Among the large variety of sciences and arts offered to students, three
             Upavedas, or sciences, were related to the education of the body:




             ❖ the Upaveda of Rigveda, called Ayurveda (the science and art of

                  sustenance, protection and maintenance of long life);

























             ❖ the Upaveda of Yajurveda, called Dhanurveda (science dealing with

                  weapons of war and art of warfare);





































             ❖ the Upaveda of Samaveda, called Gandharvaveda (science of music,

                  singing, dancing and dramatics).




                                                    (Kireet Joshi, Ed. Mystery and Excellence of the Human Body)]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Ayurveda




              Ayurveda, also known as the science for prolongation of life, makes a

              thorough study of the human body, its different types and needs, and

              accordingly proposes nutrition and specific exercises and methods for

              optimum body development, with emphasis on strength and agility.




              In Ayurveda, strength was considered the basis of health and physical

              development. By the acquisition of strength, each and every internal

              organ, the heart, the brain, the lungs, the liver and the kidneys, the

              external senses, the limbs, ought to be able to perform their functions

              without any fault or disorder.
















































                Kalaripayattu is the world’s oldest martial art and fighting

                system, which originated in Kerala. The word kalari first


                appears in the Tamil Sangam literature (c. 300BCE to

                300CE). Legend traces this martial art form to Sage

                Parashurama.]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Ayurveda and Exercise





              Exercise or vyāyāma was considered the surest means of


              acquiring strength. Therefore, the knowledge of physical

              exercises, their nature, types, exact measure of exercise,

              benefits of exercise and even contraindications and many

              details about the science of exercise were included in the


              curriculum elaborated by Ayurveda.




              Exercise was also used by the ancient physicians as a modality


              of treatment, like in modern medical science.




                                                             Dhanurveda




              Dhanurveda stands for the study of all weapons of war. To be


              able to develop high proficiency in weapons and movements of

              war, one required a whole lot of endurance, strength,

              suppleness, speed, and generally a high level of physical

              fitness. All these qualities had to be developed through


              exercises (vyāyāma) and sports.]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Training of Warriors




             The armies consisted of four divisions (chaturanga: elephants,


             horses, war-chariots, and infantry). Skills in all four were taught.



             Young warriors had also to learn the use of different kinds of


             weapons such as sword, lance, javelin, axe, mace, nooses

             (pasha), slings, etc.




             Wrestling or bāhuyuddha (literally, fighting with arms) was the

             only sort of fight without weapons. A wrestler was supposed to

             have a precise and detailed knowledge of all the vital parts of

             the body, the nerves, the muscles, the joints and ligaments.


             Only with this knowledge could he vanquish his opponent.





                                                                         Of all the arts of war, archery was

                                                                      certainly the noblest. It is the one that

                                                                     has inspired epic poets the most. They

                                                                        regarded it as a symbol of supreme

                                                                     victory and incomparable prowess. It is

                                                                     deeply embedded in the Indian culture

                                                                     and even now is still strongly engraved

                                                                         in the mind and imagination of the

                                                                      people of India. Who in India does not

                                                                    have a special place in his heart for the

                                                                      image of the two brothers, Rama and

                                                                         Lakshmana, bows resting on their

                                                                         shoulders, quivers on their backs,

                                                                     walking through the forests? Who does

                                                                    not shudder when he recalls the mighty

                                                                     Arjuna at Kurukshetra, facing the army

                                                                      of Dhritarashtra, and so overcome by


            The Trial of the Princes by                                 grief that he abandons his bow and

                      Nandlal Bose                                                  arrows? (Kireet Joshi)]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Sports and Games





             Directly linked with Dhanurveda, because of the need to develop

             strength and fitness of the warriors, were a wide range of

             exercises (vyāyāma), sports and games (krīdā). People from all

             walks of life were advised to practise them according to their


             different capabilities.




             Some of the exercises were very strenuous. For instance,


             Bharasrama consisted in lifting heavy weights made of sandbags

             of various sizes.






















































             Another exercise, still prevalent today, was Stambhasrama,

             performed on the pillar or with the help of a pillar. The athlete


             was supposed to exercise by grasping the pillar with his arms

             and legs and whirling round the pillar. This exercise is now

             known as mallakhamba.]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Sports and Games




                    Other remarkable sports included games with wild beasts


                    and the games with horses. Sports with elephants was a

                    kind of race-competition between a man and a elephant,

                    held in a specially built stadium. It was, of course, extremely

                    dangerous as the man could be trampled on by an angry


                    elephant.




                    Other kinds of sports existed where a man fought unarmed


                    with beasts such as elephants, bulls, buffaloes, etc.









































                    Asva-kanduka-krida, the sport with horses, was perhaps the

                    most sophisticated game of ancient India. It was practised in

                    a special playground of specific dimensions. The game was

                    played by two teams. The riders held strong sticks of cane


                    and had to strike a round ball made of wood covered with

                    leather. Each team tried to send the ball towards the

                    opposite goal. This game was very similar to what we now


                    call polo.]]></page></pages></Search>