<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="22"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[renaissance.aurosociety.org















                                                 NATION






                                                               AND



                                 NATIONALISM









                          Sri Aurobindo in Bande Mataram















                                                                                 Research and curation: Dr. Beloo Mehra

                                                                                  Design assistance: Biswajita Mohapatra]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[WHAT IS A NATION























      The Indian idea of nationality ought to be truer and deeper...


            What is true of the man, is true also of the nation.




        The country, the land is only the outward body of the


        nation, its annamaya kosh, or gross physical body; the mass




        of people, the life of millions who occupy and vivify the


        body of the nation with their presence, is the pranamaya



        kosh, the life-body of the nation. These two are the gross



        body, the physical manifestation of the Mother.



                                                                                                         Continued on next page...]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Within the gross body is a subtler body, the thoughts,



     the literature, the philosophy, the mental and



     emotional activities, the sum of hopes, pleasures,



     aspirations, fulfilments, the civilisation and culture,


     which make up the sukshma sharir of the nation.



     This is as much a part of the Mother’s life as the



     outward existence which is visible to the physical eyes.





                                                                                                  Continued on next page...]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[This subtle life of the nation again springs from



         a deeper existence in the causal body of the



         nation, the peculiar temperament which it has



         developed out of its ages of experience and



         which makes it distinct from others.




                                                                                                 Continued on next page...]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[These three are the bodies of the Mother, but



                    within them all is the Source of her life,



                 immortal and unchanging, of which every




                    nation is merely one manifestation, the



             universal Narayan, One in the Many of whom



                                         we are all the children.




                                                                                                            Continued on next page...]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[When, therefore, we speak of a nation, we mean



              the separate life of the millions who people the



          country, but we mean also a separate culture and



               civilisation, a peculiar national temperament



          which has become too deeply rooted to be altered


         and in all these we discover a manifestation of God



         in national life which is living, sacred and adorable.







                                                                                         ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 1115-1116]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[[The New Nationalists] are united by

         THE HEART OF                                        a common faith and a common



         NATIONALISM                                         spirit; A COMMON FAITH IN

                                                             INDIA, not in an Anglicised and


                                                             transmogrified nation


                                                             unrecognizable as Indians, but in


                                                             INDIA OF THE IMMEMORIAL


                                                             PAST, India of the clouded but


                                                             fateful present, INDIA LEONINE,


                                                             MIGHTY, crowned with her


                                                             imperial diadem of the future; A


                                                             COMMON SPIRIT OF


                                                             ENTHUSIASM, hope, the desire to


                                                             dare and do all things so that our


                                                             vision of her future may be fulfilled


                                                             greatly and soon.



            renaissance_sas                                                                              ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 1110]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[THE NEW NATIONALISM…
       THE NEW NATIONALISM…





       is an attempt to relegate the
       is an attempt to relegate the



       dominant bourgeois in us to his
       dominant bourgeois in us to his


       old obscurity, to transform the
       old obscurity, to transform the


       bourgeois into the Samurai and
       bourgeois into the Samurai and



       through him to extend the
       through him to extend the


       workings of the Samurai spirit
       workings of the Samurai spirit


       to the whole nation.
       to the whole nation.





       .e7: 1110
       .e7: 1110


                                                        Continued on next page....]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[. ...it is an attempt to
          . ...it is an attempt to


       create a new nation in
       create a new nation in

       India by reviving in spirit
       India by reviving in spirit


       & action ancient Indian
       & action ancient Indian

       character, the strong,
       character, the strong,


       great and lofty spirit of
       great and lofty spirit of

       old Aryavarta, and setting
       old Aryavarta, and setting


       it to use and mould the
       it to use and mould the

       methods and materials of
       methods and materials of


       modernity for the
       modernity for the

       freedom, greatness and
       freedom, greatness and


       well-being of a historic
       well-being of a historic

       and immortal people.
       and immortal people.





          ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 1110]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Nationalism is not a mere political



                  programme; Nationalism is a religion



             that has come from God; Nationalism is a




                  creed in which you shall have to live.






                          Let no man dare to call himself a




            Nationalist if he does so merely with a sort



                 of intellectual pride, thinking that he is



                        more patriotic, thinking that he is



                 something higher than those who do not



                              call themselves by that name.






                                                                             Continued on next page....]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[If you are going to be a Nationalist, if you are



      going to assent to this religion of Nationalism,



      you must do it in the religious spirit.





      You must remember that you are the instrument


      of God for the salvation of your own country. You



      must live as the instruments of God.



                                                                                         Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 818-819]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[THE NEW NATIONALISM…
       THE NEW NATIONALISM…



       is an attempt to relegate the dominant
       is an attempt to relegate the dominant


       bourgeois in us to his old obscurity, to
       bourgeois in us to his old obscurity, to

       transform the bourgeois into the Samurai
       transform the bourgeois into the Samurai


       and through him to extend the workings of
       and through him to extend the workings of


       the Samurai spirit to the whole nation.
       the Samurai spirit to the whole nation.




         . . it is an attempt to create a new nation in
       . . . . it is an attempt to create a new nation in

       India by reviving in spirit & action ancient
       India by reviving in spirit & action ancient

       Indian character, the strong, great and lofty
       Indian character, the strong, great and lofty

       spirit of old Aryavarta, and setting it to use and
       spirit of old Aryavarta, and setting it to use and
       mould the methods and materials of modernity
       mould the methods and materials of modernity

       for the freedom, greatness and well-being of a
       for the freedom, greatness and well-being of a

       historic and immortal people.
       historic and immortal people.

                                                        ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 1110
                                                           ~ Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 1110


                                                                          renaissance_sas]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[“When…it is said that India shall rise,



                            it is the Sanatana Dharma that shall



                            rise. When it is said that India shall be


                            great, it is the Sanatana Dharma that



                            shall be great. When it is said that



                            India shall expand and extend herself,



                            it is the Sanatana Dharma that shall



                            expand and extend itself over the


                            world. It is for the dharma and by the



                            dharma that India exists.”







                                                       (Sri Aurobindo, Uttarpara Speech)]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[है आय  स तानो! उठो, अवसर  नकल जावे नह ,



                                े
                                                                                              े

                             दखो, बड़  क  बात जग म  बगड़न पावे नह ।
                                                                         े
                        जग जान ल  क न आय  कवल नाम क ही आय  ह ,
                                                                                                े
                                              े
                                                                                             ु
                           वे नाम क अन प ही करते सदा शभ काय  ह ॥
                                            े
                                                      ु
                                                                                                                               ु
                                                                                                         ै
                                                                                                 ~ म थलीशरण ग त]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[ृ
                    उ न त तथा अवन त  क त का  नयम एक अख ड है,



                          चढ़ता  थम जो  ोम म  गरता वही मात  ड है।



                          अतएव अवन त ही हमार  कर रही उ न त-कला,



                     उ थान ही  जसका नह , उसका पतन ही  या भला?



                                                                                              ै
                                                                                      ~ म थलीशरण गु त]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[renaissance_sas
            journal.aurobharati.in


























                 हम कौन थे,  या हो गये है और  या ह गे अभी,





                 आओ,  वचार आज  मलकर ये सम याए सभी।
                                                                                                             ँ



                     य  प हम इ तहास अपना  ा त पूरा है नह ,




              हम कौन थे, इस  ान को,  फर भी अधरा है नह ॥
                                                                                                        ू



                                                                                                                                  ु
                                                                                                      ~ म थलीशरण ग त
                                                                                                             ै]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[ु
                              ू
                                                               े
         यह प यभ म   स  है इसक  नवासी 'आय ' ह ,
          व ा, कला-कौश य सबक जो  थम आचाय  ह ।
                                                          े



          स तान उनक  आज य  प हम अधोग त म पड़;
                                                                                                े

                                                                              ु
                                                                                               े
        पर  च  उनक  उ चता क आज भी कछ ह  खड़॥
                                                      े





              ै
        ~ म थलीशरण ग त
                                 ु]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[े
                                     ु
         आओ बन  शभ साधना क आज स साधक सभी,
                                                                                     े



          नज धम क  र ा कर, जीवन सफल होगा तभी।


         ससार अब दखे  क य द हम आज ह   पछड़ पड़                                                                   े
                                                                                                      े
                                     े
             ं

                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                े
         तो कल बराबर और परस   व  क आग खड़॥
                                                                                   े
                                                                                                               ु
                                                                                      ै
                                                                              ~ म थलीशरण ग त]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[...the basic spirit of Hinduism...sees the one invariable and indivisible

      Divinity in every individual being. Nationalism is simply the passionate
      aspiration for the realisation of that Divine Unity in the nation, a unity in

      which all the component individuals, however various and apparently

      unequal their functions as political, social or economic factors, are yet really
      and fundamentally one and equal. In the ideal of Nationalism which India

      will set before the world, there will be an essential equality between man and

      man, between caste and caste, between class and class, all being... different

      but equal and united parts of the Virat Purusha as realised in the nation. The
      insistent preaching of our religion and the work of the Indian Nationalist is

      to bring home to every one of his countrymen this ideal of their country’s

      religion and philosophy. We are intolerant of autocracy because it is the

      denial in politics of this essential equality, we object to the modern distortion
      of the caste system because it is the denial in society of the same essential

      equality. While we insist on reorganising the nation into a democratic unity

      politically, we recognise that the same principle of reorganisation ought to
      and inevitably will assert itself socially; ...  for the principle once realised in

      politics must inevitably assert itself in society. No monopoly racial or

      hereditary can form part of the Nationalist’s scheme of the future, his dream
      of the day for the advent of which he is striving and struggling.



                                                                                Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 679-680]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[This is the only way of inculcating a quality into a nation,


          by instilling it practically into the minds of its youth at school


          and College until it becomes an ingrained, inherent, inherited


          national quality. This is what we have to do with the modern

          ideal of patriotism in India. We have to fill the minds of our


          boys from childhood with the idea of the country, and


          present them with that idea at every turn and make their


          whole young life a lesson in the practice of the virtues which


          afterwards go to make the patriot and the citizen. If we do


          not attempt this, we may as well give up our desire to create

          an Indian nation altogether; for without such a discipline


          nationalism, patriotism, regeneration are mere words and


          ideas which can never become a part of the very soul of the


          nation and never therefore a great realised fact. Mere


          academical teaching of patriotism is of no avail.


                                                                                           Sri Aurobindo, CWSA, 7: 455]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[. . . this line of argument—that we will have a nation only


          when everyone in the country has the same religion and


          there  is  only  one  caste—is  a  fallacious  one,  for  religion


          and caste are not permanent aspects of a nation. Other


          people  argue  that  although  India  is  a  vast  country


          geographically, still it cannot be termed a nation.


          But we view it differently.







                                                                                      Continued on next page....




          2]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[renaissance_sas
                                                                                                                  journal.aurobharati.in

































          To us, by its very geography the country appears to be


          quite distinct from other countries, and that itself gives it a



          certain national character.... The inner and outer body of


          India, the customs, culture and religion of its people, have


          an independent character different from those of the rest


          of the world. It has its foundations in the ancient past.




                                                                             Sri Aurobindo, CWSA 7: 811-812]]></page></pages></Search>