<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="12"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[PERSEVERANCE




                        WORDS OF THE MOTHER]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Q:   What are the qualities needed for one to be called “a




                                           true child of the Ashram”?




                    The Mother:   Sincerity, courage, discipline,




            endurance, absolute faith in the Divine work and



                 unshakable trust in the Divine Grace. All this



                must be accompanied by a sustained, ardent,




           persevering aspiration and a boundless patience.






                                                                                                   (CWM, 16: 345-346)]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[One form of endurance is




                                  faithfulness, faithfulness to one’s





                              resolution—being faithful. One has




                              taken a resolution, one is faithful to





                              one’s resolution. This is endurance.




                                                                                       (The Mother, CWM, 8: 42)]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[All the psychological qualities can be cultivated




             as the muscles are—by regular, daily exercise.




              Above all, turn towards the Divine Force in a



           sincere aspiration and implore It to deliver you




          from your limitations. If you are sincere in your




                   will to progress, you are sure to advance.





                                     (The Mother, CWM, 16: 268-269)]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Let endurance be your watchword: teach the




             life-force in you—your vital being—not to




                       complain but to put up with all the




         conditions necessary for great achievement.





                                         ~ The Mother, CWM, 3 :136]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Nothing great is ever





        accomplished without





                          endurance.












                ~ The Mother CWM, 3: 136]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Cast away. . . all diffidence and




                                                         weakness, and resolve to




                                                   endure bravely awhile before




                                                 the great day arrives when the




                                                          long battle turns into an




                                                                everlasting victory.






                                                                 ~ The Mother, CWM, 3: 140]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[For nothing in the world can prevail against




          perseverance. And even the greatest things




              are always an accumulation of small and




                                                 untiring efforts.







                                      ~ The Mother, CWM, 2: 200]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[In this wide world, there is no lack of




                   noble work to be accomplished, nor is




             there any lack of good people to undertake




                   it; but what is very often lacking is the



                   perseverance which alone can carry it




                                            through to the end.




                                                                       ~ The Mother, CWM, 2: 202]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[. . . to those who come to tell me very light-




             heartedly, “I want to do yoga”, I reply, “Think it




             over, one may do the yoga for a number of years




             without noticing the least result. But if you want




             to do it, you must persist and persist with such a




             will that you should be ready to do it for ten




             lifetimes, a hundred lifetimes if necessary, in




             order to succeed.” I do not say it will be like that,



             but the attitude must be like that.








                                                                        ~ The Mother, CWM, 4: 251]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[For more such inspiring quick reads,



                                               visit the website of




                                            Renaissance Journal:







                               https://journal.aurobharati.in/]]></page></pages></Search>