<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="45"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[ईशोप नषद्











                                                                                           īśopaniṣad




















                                                          Introduction and Translation










                                                                                                                                  by









                                                                                                  Sri Aurobindo]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Salutation to the SO AHAM


















                              The Upanishad sets forth by pronouncing as the indispensable basis





                            of its revelations the universal nature of God. This universal nature of




                            Brahman the Eternal is the beginning and end of the Vedanta and if it





                               is not accepted, nothing the Vedanta says can have any value, as all




                                  its propositions either proceed from it or at least presuppose it; . . .




                                          with this truth in your hand as a lamp to shed light on all the





                             obscurest sayings of the Scriptures, you soon come to realise that the




                               Upanishads are a grand harmonious and perfectly luminous whole,





                                expressing in its various aspects the single and universal Truth; for




                             under the myriad contradictions of phenomena (prapancha) there is




                                                                                                    one Truth and one only.




                                                                                                                                                                                                                 (CWSA, 17: 101)]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[All the Smritis, the Puranas, the Darshanas, the






                                                    Dharmashastras, the writings of Shaktas,






                                                  Shaivas, Vaishnavas, Sauras, as well as the






                                                    whole of Buddhism and its Scriptures are







                                            merely so many explanations, comments and






                                             interpretations from different sides, of these






                                         various aspects of the one and only Truth. This






                                                      Truth is the sole foundation on which all






                                        religions can rest as on a sure and impregnable






                                              rock;—and more than a rock, for a rock may






                                                                      perish but this endures for ever.







                                                                                                                                                                                                (CWSA, 17: 101)]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Therefore is the religion of the Aryas called the







                                  Sanatana Dharma, the Law Sempiternal. Nor







                               are the Hindus in error when they declare the








                               Sruti to be eternal and without beginning and







                            the Rishis who composed the hymns to be only







                                the witnesses who saw the truth and put it in







                                           human language; for this seeing was not







                            mental sight, but spiritual. Therefore the Vedas








                                                      are justly called Sruti or revelation.











                                                                                                                                                                              (CWSA, 17: 101-102)]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Of these the Rig, Yajur, Sama & Atharvan are the






                                           fertilising rain which gave the plant of the Truth





                               nourishment and made it grow, the Brahmanas are the






                            forest in which the plant is found, the Aranyakas are the





                           soil in which it grows, the Upanishads are the plant itself,






                           roots, stalk, leaves, calix and petals, and the flower which






                              manifests itself once and for ever is the great saying SO





                                             AHAM—I AM HE which is the culmination of the






                             Upanishads. Salutation to the SO AHAM. Salutation to the





                                          Eternal who is without place, time, cause or limit,






                                                        Salutation to my Self who am the Eternal.









                                                                                                                                                                                               (CWSA, 17: 102)]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Introduction to Isha Upanishad























                              The Upanishads, being vehicles of illumination and






                                 not of instruction, composed for seekers who had






                                 already a general familiarity with the ideas of the






                                Vedic and Vedantic seers and even some personal






                                           experience of the truths on which they were






                                      founded, dispense in their style with expressed







                                        transitions of thought and the development of






                                                                     implied or subordinate notions.




                                                                                                                                                                                                            (CWSA, 17: 13)]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Every verse in the Isha Upanishad reposes on a







                                                   number of ideas implicit in the text but







                                  nowhere set forth explicitly; the reasoning also






                                        that supports its conclusions is suggested by







                                               the words, not expressly conveyed to the







                                      intelligence. The reader, or rather the hearer,






                                         was supposed to proceed from light to light,







                                     confirming his intuitions and verifying by his







                                            experience, not submitting the ideas to the







                                                                    judgment of the logical reason.






                                                                                                                                                                                                            (CWSA,17: 13)]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[The Principle of Isha Upanishad: Uncompromising






                                   Reconciliation of Uncompromising Extremes























                                  This Upanishad tries. . . to get hold of the extreme






                                             ends of the knots, disengage and place them







                                 alongside of each other in a release that will be at






                                   the same time a right placing and relation. It will






                                            not qualify or subordinate unduly any of the






                                  extremes, although it recognises a dependence of







                                                                                                    one on the other.





                                                                                                                                                                                                       (CWSA, 17: 84)]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[The pairs of opposites successively taken up by the






                                         Upanishad and resolved are, in the order of






                                                                                                    their succession:









                             1) The Conscious Lord and phenomenal Nature






                             2) Renunciation and Enjoyment






                             3) Action in Nature and Freedom in the Soul





                             4) The One stable Brahman and the multiple Movement





                             5) Being and Becoming






                             6) The Active Lord and the indifferent Akshara Brahman







                             7) Vidya and Avidya






                             8) Birth and Non-Birth






                             9) Works and Knowledge


                                                                                                                                                                                                      (CWSA, 17: 84)]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad

































                                                                           ईशा वा य मद सव य  क च जग या जगत ।
                                                                                                                 ं

                                                                                                                                                                                              ्
                                                                                                                                                                             ं


                                                                  तन  य न भ ीथा मा गधः क य  व नम ॥१॥
                                                                                                                                         ृ
                                                                       े
                                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                                          ्
                                                                                                       ु





                                                                                                                                                                                              ̇
                                                    īśā vāsyamidam sarvam yatkiñca jagatyām jagat |
                                                                                                       ̇
                                                                                                                                 ̇


                                         tena tyaktena bhuñjīthā mā gṛdhaḥ kasyasviddhanam ||]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad



























                                    All this is for habitation by the Lord, whatsoever is individual





                           universe of movement in the universal motion. By that renounced





                                     thou shouldst enjoy; lust not after any man's possession.॥1॥






                                                                                                                                                       (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)








                                                                                                                                                                                    ्

                                                         ै
                                         इस व  ग त म, इस अ य त ग तशील सम  -जगत म जो भी यह   यमान

                                           ग तशील, वय  क जगत ह - यह सबका सब ई र क आवास क  लए ह।
                                                                            ै
                                                                                                                      ै
                                                                                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             ै
                                                                                                                                                                                                                        े
                                                                                                                ्
                                                                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                         े
                                        इस सबक  याग  ारा तझ इसका उपभोग करना चा हय;  कसी भी  सर क
                                                                  े
                                                                                                             े
                                                                                                       ु
                                                                                        धन-स    पर ललचाई     मत डाल।]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                                                                            कव वह कमा ण  जजी वषत शत समाः।
                                                                                            े
                                                                                                 े
                                                                                                                                                              ्
                                                                                                                                                                          ं

                                                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                ु

                                                                   एव  व य ना यथतोऽ  त न कम  ल यत नर ॥२॥
                                                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                                                                       े

                                                                            ं
                                                                                                                े


                                                                                                                                                                                         ̇
                                                           kurvanneveha karmāṇi jijīviṣet śatam samāḥ |




                                                                     ̇
                                                     evam tvayi nānyatheto'sti na karma lipyate nare ||]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad




























                                        Doing verily works in this world one should wish to live a






                                 hundred years. Thus it is in thee and not otherwise than this;





                                                                                 action cleaves not to a man.॥2॥




                                                                                                                                                  (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)








                                                                                                             े
                                                                                                                                           ु

                                                                                                                                                                                               े
                                               इस ससार म कम करत  ए ही मन य को सौ वष जीन क  इ ा करनी

                                                                ं
                                                                                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                                                                           ै
                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                  े
                                            चा हय। ह मानव! तर  लए इस  कार का ही  वधान ह, इसस  भ   कसी
                                                              े
                                                                       े
                                                                                                                                                               े

                                                                                                   ै
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                          े
                                         और  कार का नह  ह, इस  कार कम करत  ए ही जीन क  इ ा करन स                                                                                                                                                 े
                                                                                                                                                                                               े
                                                                                                 मन य म कम का लप नह  होता।

                                                                                                          ु
                                                                                                                                                      े]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                                                                                 असया नाम त लोका अ न तमसावताः।
                                                                                             ु
                                                                                                                       े
                                                                                                                                                       े

                                                                                                                                                                                   ृ
                                                                     ता त   या भग   त य क चा महनो जनाः ॥३॥
                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                        े
                                                                            ं
                                                                                   े
                                                                                          े





                                                             asuryā nāma te lokā andhena tamasāvṛtāḥ |





                                               tāmste pretyābhigacchanti ye ke cātmahano janāḥ ||
                                                           ̇]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad





























                           Sunless are those worlds and enveloped in blind gloom whereto all





                         they in their passing hence resort who are slayers of their souls.॥3॥






                                                                                                                                                                     (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)











                                                                                                                                     े

                                                                                                                                                                       े
                                                                                      े
                                                   े
                                               व लोक सय स र हत ह और गाढ़ अ कार स आ ा दत ह। उन लोक
                                                                          ू

                                                                                                                                                                       ं
                                                 को व सभी लोग यहा स  याण करन पर प चत ह जो कोई भी अपनी
                                                                                                                                                                                े

                                                               े
                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                         ं
                                                                                                                                                  े
                                                                                                            आ मा का हनन करत ह।
                                                                                                                                                                      े]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                                                                  अनजदक मनसो जवीयो नन वा आ वन पवमषत ।
                                                                                                                                                                                        ू
                                                                                                                                                                         ु
                                                                                                                                                                                  ्
                                                                                                                                           ै
                                                                                                                                                   े
                                                                                           ं

                                                                                                                                                                                                           ्

                                                                                       े
                                                                             े
                                                      त ावतोऽ यान य त  त त त  म पो मात र ा दधा त ॥४॥
                                                                                                       े
                                                                                                                                ्



                                   anejadekam manaso javīyo nainaddevā āpnuvan pūrvamarṣat |
                                                                         ̇




                                   taddhāvato'nyānatyeti tiṣṭhat tasminnapo mātariśvā dadhāti ||]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad



























                           One unmoving that is swifter than Mind, That the Gods reach not,





                        for It progresses ever in front. That, standing, passes beyond others





                            as they run. In That the Master of Life establishes the Waters.॥4॥




                                                                                                                                                                  (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)







                                                                                                                                                                 े
                                                                                                                             े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      ै
                                                                                                                                                                                                                             े
                                                                                                                                                                       े
                                          वह अचल, अचलायमान एकमव    मन स वगव र, अ य धक वगवाला ह।
                                                                                                                                  ँ
                                                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                     े
                                              उस एकमव तक दवता नह  प च पात,  य  क वह सदव उनस आग-आग                                                                                                                                                    े
                                                                                                                                                                                                 ै
                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                      े
                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                  े
                                             प च जाता ह। वह ठहरा  आ भी दौड़त  ए  सर  को पार कर आग  नकल
                                                      ँ
                                                                                                                                                        े
                                                                                 ै

                                                                                             ्
                                               जाता ह। उस तत म जीवन-श   का  वामी वाय जलधारा  को  ा पत
                                                                                                                                                                                 ु
                                                                    ै

                                                                                                                                     करता ह।
                                                                                                                                                           ै]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                                                                                         तदज त त ज त तद्  र त   तक।
                                                                                                                                                                                   े
                                                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                                         ै
                                                                                                 े

                                                                          तद तर य सव य त  सव या य बा तः ॥५॥










                                                                       tadejati tannaijati tad dūre tadvantike |





                                                   tadantarasya sarvasya tadu sarvasyāsya bāhyataḥ ||]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad






























                                       That moves and That moves not; That is far and the same is






                                 near; That is within all this and That also is outside all this.॥5॥






                                                                                                                                                           (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)














                                           वह ग त करता ह और ग त नह  भी करता; वह  र ह और पास भी ह; इस
                                                                                                                                                                                      ै
                                                                                        ै
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                ै


                                                                                  सबक भीतर ह और इस सबक बाहर भी ह।
                                                                                                                                                                                                   ै
                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                         ै
                                                                                                                                                                  े]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                                                                                य त सवा ण भता न आ म यवानप य त।
                                                                                                                                                               े

                                                                                                                         ू
                                                                                            ु
                                                                                                                                                                          ु
                                                                               सवभतष चा मान ततो न  वजग सत ॥६॥
                                                                                                                                                                ु
                                                                                                                                                                                 े
                                                                                                                                                                     ु
                                                                                                                               ं
                                                                                               ू

                                                                                                   े
                                                                                                        ु


                                                               yastu sarvāṇi bhūtāni ātmanyevānupaśyati |





                                                           sarvabhūteṣu cātmānam tato na vijugupsate ||
                                                                                                                                           ̇]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad






























                                      But he who sees everywhere the Self in all existences and all






                                    existences in the Self, shrinks not thereafter from aught.॥6॥





                                                                                                                                                            (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)












                                   पर त जो सभी भत  या स ा  को परम आ मा म ही दखता ह और सभी भत
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                               ू
                                                                                                                                                                                                            ै
                                                                                                                                                                                        े
                                                  ु
                                                                                  ू


                                      या स ा  म परम आ मा को, वह  फर सव  एक ही आ मा क   य  दशन

                                                                                                                                                                                                              े

                                                                       क प ात,  कसी स कतराता नह , घणा नह  करता।
                                                                                                                           े
                                                                                                ्
                                                                                                                                                                         ृ
                                                                           े]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad
































                                                                         य  मन सवा ण भता न आ मवाभद्  वजानतः।

                                                                                                                         ू
                                                                                                                                                        ै
                                                                                                                                                                    ू
                                                                                            ्
                                                                          त  को मोहः कः शोक एक वमनप यतः ॥७॥
                                                                                                                                                                  ु








                                                     yasmin sarvāṇi bhūtāni ātmaivābhūd vijānataḥ |





                                                     tatra ko mohaḥ kaḥ śoka ekatvamanupaśyataḥ ||]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad




























                    He in whom it is the Self - Being that has become all existences that are





                    Becomings, for he has the perfect knowledge, how shall he be deluded,






                                   whence shall he have grief who sees everywhere oneness ?॥7॥






                                                                                                                                                              (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)







                                                                                                                                                                                   ु
                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                    े
                                                                                                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                              े
                                        पण  ान,  व ान स स   होन क कारण  जस मन य क अ दर यह परमो

                                             ू
                                        चतना जाग गयी ह  क  वय  आ मस ा ही, परम आ मा ही  वय सभी भत,
                                                                                                                          ू
                                              े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                ू
                                                                                          ै
                                                                                                                                                                                                                          ं

                                                                                                                                                                                                                   े
                                                                                                                                                                                                            ै
                                                                                                                                                             ु
                                                                                                                  ं
                                                                                                    ू
                                                                                                                                     ै
                                            सभी स ाएं या स  तया बना ह, उस मन य म  फर मोह कस होगा, शोक
                                                                        कहा स होगा जो सव  आ मा क  एकता ही दखता ह।
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     ै
                                                                                    ं

                                                                                                                                                                                                 े
                                                                                           े]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                                                                स पयगा  मकायम णम ना वर श मपाप व म ।

                                                                                               ु
                                                                                                                                                                ं
                                                                                                                                                                                                                ्
                                                                                                                                                                       ु

                            क वमनीषी प रभूः  वय याथात यतोऽथान  दधात शा ती यः समा यः ॥८॥

                                                                                                                                                     ्
                                                                                                                                                                               ्

                                                                                                     ू





                                                         sa paryagācchukramakāyamavraṇamasnāviram
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     ̇




                                                                                             śuddhamapāpaviddham |





                            kavirmanīṣī paribhūḥ svayambhūryāthātathyato'rthān vyadadhāt





                                                                                           śāśvatībhyaḥ samābhyaḥ ||]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad


























                         It is He that has gone abroad -That which is bright, bodiless, without scar of




                                     imperfection, without sinews, pure, unpierced by evil. The Seer, the





                            Thinker, the One who becomes everywhere, the Self - existent has ordered




                                 objects perfectly according to their nature from years sempiternal.॥8॥




                                                                                                                                                               (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)




                                                                                                      ै

                                                                                                                             ्
                                                    ु
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           े
                                       वह प ष ही सव   ा त ह - वह तत जो  यो तमय, शरीर-र हत, अपणता क  च

                                                                                                                                                                                                           ू
                                       या दाग स श य,  नाय एव नस-नाड़ी स र हत और श  ह एव पाप स  बधा नह  ह।
                                                                                                    ं
                                                                                                                                   े
                                                                                                                                                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                      ै
                                                                                                                                                                                       ं
                                                                                                                                                                   ु
                                                                                                                                                                              ै
                                                                                           ु
                                                                    ू
                                                              े


                                                                                                                                                          ु
                                         सवदश , मनीषवान वह एकमव जो सव  सब कछ हो जाता या बन जाता ह, उस
                                                                                        ्
                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           ै
                                                          ्
                                       वयसत प ष न ही सनातन वष  स, अना द काल स सभी पदाथ  को उनक  वभाव
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     े
                                                 ं
                                                                                                                         े
                                                               ु
                                                                             े
                                                                                                                                                                 े
                                                    क अन प पणतया ठ क-ठ क, यथातथ  प म  व  त कर रखा ह।

                                                                                    ू
                                                                                                                                                                                                                         ै

                                                        े
                                                                    ु]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad

































                                                                                    अ  तमः   वश  त यऽ व ामपासत।
                                                                                                  ं
                                                                                                                                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                        ु
                                                                                                                                                 े

                                                                             ततो भय इव त तमो य उ  व ाया रताः ॥९॥
                                                                                                ू
                                                                                                                                                                     ं
                                                                                                                     े








                                                        andham tamaḥ praviśanti ye'vidyāmupāsate |
                                                                                  ̇




                                                                                                                                                                                 ̇
                                                         tato bhūya iva te tamo ya u vidyāyām ratāḥ ||]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad






























                               Into a blind darkness they enter who follow after the Ignorance,




                                 they as if into a greater darkness who devote themselves to the






                                                                                                    Knowledge alone.॥9॥




                                                                                                                                           (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)











                                                                                                                                 े


                                                                                                                                             े
                                                                                                   ु
                                                                                                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                          े

                                               जो अ व ा का अनसरण करत ह व घोर अ कार म  वश करत ह। और
                                                                                                                                                                        े
                                                                                                                                        े

                                                                                                                            े
                                                          े
                                            जो कवल  व ा म ही रत रहत ह व मान  उसस भी अ धक घोर अ कार म

                                                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                                             वश करत ह।]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                                                                                         अ यदवा  व याऽ यदा र व या।

                                                                                                          े



                                                                            इ त श म धीराणा य न त  चच  र ॥१०॥
                                                                                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                                               ं
                                                                                              ु
                                                                                                    ु





                                                                     anyadevāhurvidyayā'nyadāhuravidyayā |





                                                             iti śuśruma dhīrāṇām ye nastadvicacakṣire ||
                                                                                                                                    ̇]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad




























                        Other, verily, it is said, is that which comes by the Knowledge, other





                         that which comes by the Ignorance; this is the lore we have received






                                     from the wise who revealed That to our understanding.॥10॥




                                                                                                                                                            (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)









                                                                                                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                                                ै
                                                                                                       ै
                                     व ा स जो  ा त होता ह वह  सरा ही ह, ऐसा  ानी कहत ह। अ व ा स जो
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       े

                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                      े
                                                                                                                                                                                    ु

                                                                                                         ै
                                                                   ै
                                  ा त होता ह वह और ही ह, ऐसा  ानी कहत ह। यह   त ान हमन  ा नय  स                                                                                                                                                    े
                                               ा त  कया ह  ज ह न हमारी ब   क सम  उसको  का शत  कया।
                                                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                                  ु
                                                                                                         े
                                                                                  ै]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad

































                                                                                       व ा चा व ा च य त दोभय सह।
                                                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                                                                                           ं



                                                                         अ व या म य ती वा  व याऽमतम त ॥११॥

                                                                                                                                                                              ु
                                                                                                                                                               ृ
                                                                                                         ृ
                                                                                                                ुं
                                                                                                                                                                                  े





                                                                                                                                                                                          ̇
                                                               vidyāñcāvidyāñca yastadvedobhayam saha |




                                                         avidyayā mṛtyum tīrtvā vidyayā'mṛtamaśnute ||
                                                                                                                 ̇]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad






























                                         He who knows That as both in one, the Knowledge and the




                                     Ignorance, by the Ignorance crosses beyond death and by the






                                                                             Knowledge enjoys Immortality.॥11॥





                                                                                                                                                   (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)










                                                                                                                    ै

                                                 ्
                              जो तत को इस  प म जानता ह  क वह एक साथ  व ा और अ व ा दोन  ह, वह
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           ै

                                               अ व ा स म य को पार कर  व ा स अमरता का आ वादन करता ह।
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    ै
                                                                                                                                               े
                                                                          े
                                                                                 ृ
                                                                                        ु]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad

































                                                                                 अ  तमः   वश  त यऽस  तमपासत।
                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                               ं
                                                                                                                                                               ू
                                                                                                                                                                           ु
                                                                                                                                                                                            े
                                                                          ततो भय इव त तमो य उ स  या रताः ॥१२॥
                                                                                                                                                          ू
                                                                                                                                                                    ं
                                                                                             ू
                                                                                                                  े








                                                                               ̇
                                                     andham tamaḥ praviśanti ye'sambhūtimupāsate |




                                                       tato bhūya iva te tamo ya u sambhūtyām ratāḥ ||
                                                                                                                                                                                           ̇]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad





























                                          Into a blind darkness they enter who follow after the Non -





                                   Birth, they as if into a greater darkness who devote themselves





                                                                                                    to the Birth alone.॥12॥




                                                                                                                                      (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)









                                      जो अज म, ज माभाव क  अव ा का अनसरण करत ह व घोर अ कार म

                                                                                                                                                          ु
                                                                                                                                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                                                     े

                                                                                                                                                               े


                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       े
                                             े
                                                                                                        े
                                                                   े

                                     वश करत ह। और जो कवल ज म,  क त क अ दर ज म म ही रत रहत ह व                                                                                                                                                       े
                                                                                                                                                ृ
                                                                  मानो उसस भी अ धक घोर अ कार म  वश करत ह।

                                                                                                                                                                                       े
                                                                                                 े

                                                                                                                                                                                                            े]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad

































                                                                                   अ यदवा ः स वाद यदा रस वात ।
                                                                                                                                                                                         ्
                                                                                                     े



                                                                            इ त श म धीराणा य न त  चच  र ॥१३॥
                                                                                                                               ं
                                                                                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                              ु
                                                                                                    ु





                                                      anyadevāhuḥ sambhavādanyadāhurasambhavāt |





                                                             iti śuśruma dhīrāṇām ye nastadvicacakṣire ||
                                                                                                                                    ̇]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad





























                          Other, verily, it is said, is that which comes by the Birth, other that





                       which comes by the Non-Birth; this is the lore we have received from






                                              the wise who revealed That to our understanding.॥13॥





                                                                                                                                                               (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)










                                                                                                                                                                                                    े
                                                                                                                                                    ै
                                                                                                             ै
                                          ज म स जो  ा त होता ह वह अ य ही ह, ऐसा  ानी कहत ह; अज म स जो
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        े

                                                               े
                                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                                        ु

                                                                                                              ै
                                                                        ै
                                      ा त होता ह वह और ही ह, ऐसा  ानी कहत ह; यह   त ान हमन  ा नय  स                                                                                                                                                    े
                                                                                      ै
                                                  ा त  कया ह  ज ह न हमारी ब   क सम  तत को  का शत  कया।
                                                                                                                                      ु
                                                                                                                                                    े
                                                                                                             े
                                                                                                                                                                                  ्]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad

































                                                                                  स  त च  वनाश च य त दोभय सह।
                                                                                                                                                                                ं
                                                                                               ू
                                                                                                                                                               े


                                                                         वनाशन म य ती वा स  याऽमतम त ॥१४॥

                                                                                                                                              ू
                                                                                                                                                                               ु
                                                                                                                                                               ृ
                                                                                                      ृ
                                                                                           े
                                                                                                             ुं
                                                                                                                                                                                   े


                                                                                                                                                                                                ̇
                                                  sambhūtiñca vināśañca yastadvedobhayam saha |




                                               vināśena mṛtyum tīrtvā sambhūtyā'mṛtamaśnute ||
                                                                                                        ̇]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad





























                              He who knows That as both in one, the Birth and the dissolution





                                      of Birth, by the dissolution crosses beyond death and by the






                                                                                      Birth enjoys Immortality.॥14॥





                                                                                                                                        (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)










                                                                                                                                      ै

                                                                   ्
                                                जो तत को इस  प म जानता ह  क वह एक साथ ज म और ज म का


                                                                                                                                           े
                                                                                                                                                                                               े
                                                                                                                                                                                                     ृ
                                                                                                                                                            े
                                                                                                                                                                                                             ु
                                                         े
                                                                                                          ै
                                            उ द या अ त दोन  ह, वह ज म क उ द या अ त स म य को पार कर
                                                                                                                                                                                                ै
                                                                                                           े
                                                                                      ज म स अमरता का आ वादन करता ह।]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad





































                                                                                  हर मयन पा ण स य या प हत मखम ।
                                                                                                        े
                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                                                                                                            ्
                                                                                                                                                                                ु
                                                                                                                                                                          ं
                                                                             तत  व पष पावण स यधमाय   य ॥१५॥
                                                                                                                                ु
                                                                                                                                                                              े

                                                                                                                          ृ
                                                                                               ं
                                                                                                     ू
                                                                                       ्



                                                                                                                                                                                 ̇
                                                   hiraṇmayena pātreṇa satyasyāpihitam mukham |




                                                 tat tvam pūṣannapāvṛṇu satyadharmāya dṛṣṭaye ||
                                                                           ̇]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad































                          The face of Truth is covered with a brilliant golden lid; that do thou





                                       remove, O Fosterer, for the law of the Truth, for sight.॥15॥






                                                                                                                                                         (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)














                                                     स य का मख चमक ल सनहर ढ कन स ढका ह; ह पोषक सयदव!
                                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                        ू
                                                                                                                                                                                      ै
                                                                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                                                  े
                                                                                  ु

                                                                                                                                                                                                                                 े
                                                                                                                  े
                                                                                                                         ु
                                                                                                                                                                                                                            ू
                                                                                                                                                                                                      े

                                                                         े
                                                       स य क  वधान क  उपल   क  लए, सा ात दशन क  लए त वह
                                                                                                                                         े
                                                                                                                                                                                ्
                                                                                                                ढ कन अव य हटा द।
                                                                                                                                                                         े]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad
































                                                                        पष कष यम सय  ाजाप य  ह र मीन समह।
                                                                                      े


                                                                                                                   ू
                                                                            ू
                                                                                                                                                                                     ्
                                                                                                                                                                                                 ू
                                                                                                                                                             ू
                                                                                                                                                             ं
                                                                                                                                                                        े
                                                                                                                           ं
                                                                                                        ्
                                                                                     े
                                                                                तजो यत त  प क याणतम त  प या म
                                                                                                              े
                                                                                      योऽसावसौ प षः सोऽहम  म ॥१६॥
                                                                                                                          ु






                                      pūṣannekarṣe yama sūrya prājāpatya vyūha raśmīn samūha |





                                                              tejo yat te rūpam kalyāṇatamam tatte paśyāmi
                                                                                                                     ̇
                                                                                                                                                                        ̇



                                                                                  yo'sāvasau puruṣaḥ so'hamasmi ||]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad




























                                        O Fosterer, O sole Seer, O Ordainer, O illumining Sun, O power of




                                    the Father of creatures, marshal thy rays, draw together thy light; the




                                         Lustre which is thy most blessed form of all, that in Thee I behold.





                                                                         The Purusha there and there, He am I.॥16॥




                                                                                                                                              (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)






                                                                                                                                         ं
                                                                                                             े

                                                                                                                                                                                                                  े
                                                                                                                                                                    े
                                                                                                                                                                                                       ू
                                             े
                                         ह पोषक, ह एकमा    ा, ह  वधाता एव  नय ता, ह  काशदाता सय, ह  जाप त क
                                                                     े
                                           ( ा णय  एव  जा  क  पता क ) श  ! अपनी  करण  को  हब  एव  व  त
                                                                                                                                                                                                ू
                                                                                                  े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                       ं
                                                                         ं
                                                                                                                                                                                      े
                                                                                                                                                                        े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     े
                                                                                                                                                                                                 े
                                                                                                                                     ु
                                                    कर, अपन  काश को एक  एव प ीभत कर ल जो तज तरा सबस अ धक
                                                                             े
                                                                                                                               ं
                                                                                                                                                    ू
                                               क याणकारी  प ह, तरा वही  प म दखता  । वहा, वहा जो प ष ह वही   म।
                                                                                                       े
                                                                                                                                                                                                                   ै

                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    ँ
                                                                                               ै
                                                                                                                                                                                        ं
                                                                                                                                                                           ं
                                                                                                                                                             ं
                                                                                                                                                                                                      ु

                                                                                                                                            े]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad



































                                                                                          वायर नलममतमथद भ मात शरीरम ।
                                                                                                                                                ं
                                                                                                                                             े
                                                                                                                              ृ
                                                                                                                                                                  ं
                                                                                                                                                                       ं
                                                                                                                                                                                            ्
                                                                                                     ु
                                                                          ॐ  तो  मर कत  मर  तो  मर कत  मर ॥१७॥
                                                                                                                                                                              ं
                                                                                                                                                                       ृ
                                                                                                                         ं
                                                                                                                  ृ







                                                                                                                                                                                                           ̇
                                                                                                                                                                                              ̇
                                                                                                                                                           ̇
                                                           vāyuranilamamṛtamathedam bhasmāmtam śarīram |


                                                                                                                                                                                                                   ̇
                                                                                                                              ̇
                                                     om krato smara kṛtam smara krato smara kṛtam smara ||]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad




























                           The Breath of things is an immortal Life, but of this body ashes are






                              the end. OM! OWill, remember, that which was done remember!





                                           O Will, remember, that which was done remember.॥17॥





                                                                                                                                                                          y Sri Aurobindo)
                                                                                                                                                        (Translation b






                                          व त  का  ाण, वाय, अमर जीवनत व ह, पर त इस का अ त ह भ म।
                                                                                                      ु
                                                                                                                                                              ै
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           ै
                                                                                                                                                                                 ु
                                                       ु
                                            ओ३म। ह  द  सक पश  !  मरण कर, जो  कया था उस  मरण कर!
                                                                                                                                                                                                           े
                                                                       े
                                                                                             ं



                                                      ह  द  सक पश  ,  मरण कर,  कय  ए कम का  मरण कर।
                                                           े

                                                                                 ं
                                                                                                                                                               े]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad


































                                                                 अ न नय सपथा राय अ मान  व ा न दव वयना न  व ान ।
                                                                                                                                              ्
                                                                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                                        े
                                                                                                ु
                                                                                                                                                                                          ु
                                                                                                                                                                                                                           ्
                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                                                                                    े
                                                                                                                                                        ं

                                                                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                        ु
                                                                       ु
                                                                   ययो य म  राणमनो भ य ा त नमउ    वधम ॥१८॥
                                                                                                                                          ू
                                                                                                                            े


                                          agne naya supathā rāye asmān viśvāni deva vayunāni vidvān |





                                yuyodhyasmajjuhurāṇameno bhūyiṣṭhām te namauktim vidhema ||
                                                                                                                                                                                                                        ̇
                                                                                                                                                                        ̇]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[īśopaniṣad




























                            O god Agni, knowing all things that are manifested, lead us by the





                            good path to the felicity; remove from us the devious attraction of






                      sin. To thee completest speech of submission we would dispose.॥18॥





                                                                                                                                                            (Translation by Sri Aurobindo)








                                                                                                                                                                           े
                                                                                                              े
                                                                                                                                  े
                                                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                                                                      े
                                                                                                ु
                                                                                                                                                                                                    ु
                                                                                                                                                                                                                     े
                                                        सब    व त  क जानन वाल ह अ  नदव! हम सपथ स, उ म
                                                                                                                                                                                             े

                                                                                                                                                                           ु
                                                                                                                                                                                                    ू


                                                                             े
                                                                                                                                े
                                                          माग स आन द क  ओर ल चल; पाप का क टलतापण आकषण

                                                                                  े
                                                                   हमस हटा द,  र कर द। तर   त अ तनमन (समपण) क

                                                                                                                                े
                                                                                                    े
                                                                                                                                          े
                                                                                                                                             े
                                                                                       सवा पण वाणी ( तो ) हम  नव दत कर।

                                                                                                                                                                               े


                                                                                                             ू]]></page></pages></Search>