<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="20"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[How can we make our sleep more restful
          and not wake up fatigued and tired? How

             can we use sleep to provide a stable
           foundation for our waking hours? Let us

             together explore the realm of sleep!






        Sleep is the school one must pass through if

         one knows how to learn one’s lesson there,

              so that the inner being may become

               independent of the physical form,

         conscious in its own right and master of its

                                 own life.


                              -The Mother]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[A MINI COMPILATION








         The Need for Sleep




         Rest is absolutely necessary for the

         body and still more for the nervous

         system; not only for working but for

         sadhana rest to the body and the

         nerves is essential. If you allow them

         to be strained and tired, they will not

         be able to adapt themselves readily

         for the required change, all sorts of

         things, confusion, suggestions etc. are
         likely to come into a tired nervous


         system. They too must be strong and
         at peace.

         - Sri Aurobindo (CWSA 31: 439)








      Page 1                                                                                         Sleep]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Getting into Sleep...




         The sleep before 12 [AM] is supposed

         to be the best.




                                        *



         To sleep without a burdened stomach

         is obviously more healthy, both

         psychologically and physically.
         - Sri Aurobindo (CWSA 31: 443)










         ...it [reading a novel before going to

         bed] threw you into a tamasic

         consciousness and consequently the

         sleep was heavy in a gross

         subconsciousness and the fatigue was

         the result.

                                        *

        Page 2                                                                                   Sleep]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[You should not jump up from sleep.
           Rise quietly and take a little time. You

           must give time for the consciousness

           to come back fully into the body.

           - Sri Aurobindo (CWSA 31: 444)































        Page 3                                                                                 Sleep]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[How to Rest Before Sleeping?




         I would advise you all to rest before

         going to sleep. But then you must

         know how to rest.




         There are many ways of doing it. Here

         is one: first of all, put your body at
         ease, comfortably stretched out on a

         bed or in an easy-chair. Then try to

         relax your nerves, all together or one

         by one, till you have obtained

         complete relaxation. This done, and

         while your body lies limp like a rag on

         the bed, make your brain silent and

         immobile, till it is no longer conscious

         of itself. Then slowly, imperceptibly,

         pass from this state into sleep. When

         you wake up the next morning, you




        Page  4                                                                                   Sleep]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[will be full of energy. On the contrary,

         if you go to bed completely tired and

         without relaxing yourself, you will fall
         into a heavy, dull and unconscious

         sleep in which the vital will lose all its

         energies.




         It is possible that you may not obtain

         an immediate result, but persevere.

         - The Mother (CWM 15: 132)



























        Page 5                                                                                   Sleep]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Learning How to Sleep...




         Naturally, if you keep yourself from

         sleeping, you won’t sleep. I always tell

         those who complain of not being able to

         sleep, “Meditate then and you will end
         up by sleeping.” It is better to fall

         asleep while concentrating than “like

         that”, scattered and strewn without

         knowing even where one is.




         To sleep well one must learn how to

         sleep.




         If one is physically very tired, it is better

         not to go to sleep immediately,

         otherwise one falls into the inconscient.
         If one is very tired, one must stretch out

         on the bed, relax, loosen all the nerves

         one after another until one becomes

         like a rumpled cloth in one’s


        Page 9                                                                                   Sleep]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[bed, as though one had neither bones

        nor muscles. When one has done that,

        the same thing must be done in the

        mind. Relax, do not concentrate on

        any idea or try to solve a problem or

        ruminate on impressions, sensations or

        emotions you had during the day. All

        that must be allowed to drop off

        quietly: one gives oneself up, one is

        indeed like a rag. When you have

        succeeded in doing this, there is
        always a little flame, there—that flame

        never goes out and you become

        conscious of it when you have

        managed this relaxation. And all of a

        sudden this little flame rises slowly

        into an aspiration for the divine life,

        the truth, the consciousness of the

        Divine, the union with the inner being,





        Page 6                                                                                  Sleep]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[it goes higher and higher, it rises,

        rises, like that, very gently. Then

        everything gathers there, and if at

        that moment you fall asleep, you have

        the best sleep you could possibly have.

        I guarantee that if you do this

        carefully, you are sure to sleep, and

        also sure that instead of falling into a

        dark hole you will sleep in light, and
        when you get up in the morning you

        will be fresh, fit, content, happy and

        full of energy for the day.

        - The Mother (CWM 4: 351-52)



















        Page 7                                                                                     Sleep]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Aspiration Towards a Higher and Vaster

       Consciousness




       Sleep must not be a fall into

       unconsciousness which makes the body

       heavy instead of refreshing it. Eating

       with moderation and abstaining from

       all excess greatly reduces the need to

       spend many hours in sleep; however,

       the quality of sleep is much more

       important than its quantity. In order

       to have a truly effective rest and
       relaxation during sleep, it is good as a

       rule to drink something before going

       to bed, a cup of milk or soup or fruit-

       juice, for instance. Light food brings a

       quiet sleep. One should, however,

       abstain from all copious meals, for

       then the sleep becomes agitated and

       is disturbed by nightmares,



        Page 8                                                                                     Sleep]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[or else is dense, heavy and dulling. But

        the most important thing of all is to

        make the mind clear, to quieten the
        emotions and calm the effervescence

        of desires and the preoccupations

        which accompany them. If before

        retiring to bed one has talked a lot or

        had a lively discussion, if one has read

        an exciting or intensely interesting

        book, one should rest a little without

        sleeping in order to quieten the

        mental activity, so that the brain does

        not engage in disorderly movements

        while the other
















        Page 9                                                                                 Sleep]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[parts of the body alone are asleep.

         Those who practise meditation will do

         well to concentrate for a few minutes

         on a lofty and restful idea, in an
         aspiration towards a higher and

         vaster consciousness. Their sleep will

         benefit greatly from this and they will

         largely be spared the risk of falling

         into unconsciousness while they sleep.

         - The Mother (CWM 12: 52)




















        Page 10                                                                                  Sleep]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[What We Do in Our Waking State

         Percolates in Our Sleep




         In the sleep what holds the body is the

         subconscient—and the subconscient

         acts according to the already formed

         present habits or else the impressions

         left by past thoughts, feelings,

         memories, activities. If the thought of

         the Mother and her force and working

         are fixed in the conscious hours, then

         it will be easier to bring it into the
         subconscient.

         - Sri Aurobindo (CWSA 31: 449)














        Page 11                                                                                      Sleep]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Connecting with the Place of True Rest




         A long unbroken sleep is necessary

         because there are just ten minutes of

         the whole into which one enters into a
         true rest—a sort of Sachchidananda

         immobility of the consciousness—and

         that it is which really restores the

         system. The rest of the time is spent

         first in travelling through various

         states of consciousness towards that

         and then coming out of it back

         towards the waking state.This fact of

         the ten minutes true rest has been

         noted by medical men, but of course

         they know nothing about
         Sachchidananda!

         - Sri Aurobindo (CWSA 31: 442)










        Page 12                                                                                     Sleep]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Continuing Our Inner-Work in Sleep

         Too!




         If the sleep becomes conscious even

         for a time, then experience and

         sadhana of itself can go on in the

         sleep state and not only in the waking
         condition.




                                        *



         It is usually only if there is much

         activity of sadhana in the day that it

         extends also into the sleep state.

         - Sri Aurobindo (CWSA 31: 445)














        Page 13                                                                                   Sleep]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Making Sleep a Conscious Inner State





         It is better to go to sleep and make it
         a discipline to become conscious in


         your sleep. Sleep may be only a habit,
         but it is a necessary habit at present

         and the thing to do is not to suppress,

         but to transform it into a conscious

         inner state.

         - Sri Aurobindo (CWSA 31: 448)























        Page 14                                                                                   Sleep]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[You must rest—but a rest of concentrated

         force, not of diluted non-resistance to the

         adverse forces. A rest that is a power, not the


         rest of weakness.

         - The Mother (CWM 15: 132)

























        Page 15                                                                                   Sleep]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[This mini-compilation is just a taste of the full
           compilation on Sleep from the luminous words of
           Sri Aurobindo and the Mother and their Integral Yoga.

           To read the full compilation, click here.














                                Abbreviations used-
             CWSA - THE COMPLETE WORKS OF SRI AUROBINDO
               CWM - THE COLLECTED WORKS OF THE MOTHER]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[W: ay.aurosociety.org
                        FB: fb.com/AuroYouth

                   IG: instagram.com/auro_youth]]></page></pages></Search>